You're procrastinating way too freaking
much. You know it and I know it. So
today, we're going to fix that. And
look, it's not because you're lazy. It's
not because you don't care. It's because
procrastination isn't what you think it
is. It's actually two separate problems
happening at the same time, and nobody
teaches you how to solve either. I get
it. I have pretty hardcore ADHD, which
makes it pretty impossible for me to do
anything without getting distracted. But
despite all of that, I've been able to
build a nine-figure empire and help
thousands of other entrepreneurs do the
exact same. And I can tell you, you
don't just beat procrastination with
brute force. There are ways to hack your
brain into being 10 times more
productive, if not more. So in this
video, I'm going to show you why you
keep getting distracted, how to
eliminate those distractions, how to
stay locked in when you're actually
doing the work, and how to permanently
wire these systems into your brain so
they run on autopilot. Starting with
point number one, why you actually
procrastinate in the first place. See,
most people think distractions come from
the outside. I'm talking emails and the
pinging and the phone buzzing and Slack
notifications going off, but that's not
true. The real problem is internal
triggers. My friend Nir Eyal, an author
of Indistractable, says that we reach
for distractions to escape boredom,
loneliness, fear, fatigue, uncertainty.
We use these distractions that might
make you think you're productive, but
you're actually using them to keep
yourself busy doing stuff that doesn't
do anything. People avoid things that
might stress them out. I remember Jeff
Bezos said, he says, "Stress primarily
comes from not taking action over
something that you can [music] have some
control over." So the stress that you
created by not doing the thing is where
the stress came from versus just saying,
"I got control over this. Let me do
something with it." So now that you
understand the reasons behind
distractions, we need to move forward.
We need to figure out what all those
distractions actually [music] are so you
can attack them. Which takes us to the
next point. Point number two, signal
versus noise. Steve Jobs used to talk
about this idea of focusing on what
really matters, which is signal versus
what really doesn't, which is the noise.
Signal in many ways follows the Pareto
principle, which is 20% of the work
actually drives 80% of the results.
The noise is everything else, and it
falls into two categories.
The busy work, keeping you busy but
doesn't actually do anything, or the
distraction, the vices, the video games,
the talking with your friends for hours,
reading the news, watching the sports
games. These are all things that just
keep you distracted from actually
getting the work done. I remember I was
running my first company, I was busy,
working 100-hour weeks, and then I hired
a coach, and my coach analyzed my
calendar. And when he looked at it, he
said, "Hey, did you know you spend 70%
of your time in meetings that are just
like getting updates, and honestly,
you're not producing any results? Sales,
which drives revenue, was only 10% of my
calendar." See, he could see the signal
in all the noise, and I was pretending
not to see it, but the truth was is that
I was just allowing myself to be
distracted because it felt productive.
That's why I always go back to a simple
premise. If you show me your calendar
and your bank account, I will show you
what's important to you. So, here's what
I want you to do right now. Go grab
something to write with. It can be a
blank piece of paper, or pull out your
phone and start a new note, but find
something to write with. Number one,
draw two columns. Just put a direct line
down the middle of that page, one
labeled signal, the other one labeled
noise. The second thing is I want you to
think about everything that you did in
the last couple weeks, and I want you to
write it down on that piece of paper in
those two columns. It's either noise or
it's signal. So, what you'll probably
notice is you'll have a lot of stuff in
the noise column. And what you want to
do is get most of your week to be in the
signal column. I know a lot of business
owners that are trying to scale past
seven figures, and they're stuck in the
noise. They can't find their way out.
That's why I created my scale your
business workbook. It teaches you how to
buy back your time and get out of the
noise. And if you want my step-by-step
process, just find me on Instagram and
message me the word scale YouTube, and
I'll send it right over to you. So, now
you know what you're spending your time
on when it comes to single to noise. You
can see exactly where you're wasting
time, and you can probably diagnose some
of the stuff in the noise column that
you need to cut to get rid of. So, how
do you actually do that?
Point number three, eliminating
distractions. The way we become more
productive is first, we have to make it
difficult for you to get distracted, and
we have to break out the habits of
defaulting to devices. So, here are two
ways you can do this. I call it the
friction rule. Either we add friction to
make it hard, or we remove friction to
make it work. So, the first thing is we
got to procrastinate the distraction
itself. If you're about to go open up
Instagram and go doom scroll, I want you
to at least make a commitment to
yourself. And I know it sounds weird cuz
you're like, "Well, I was about to do
it. How am I going to not do it?" I'm
telling you just give yourself 10
minutes.
I'll actually allow you to do it. If you
can go, "Hey, I'm going to wait 10
minutes until I go and I doom scroll on
Instagram cuz I really want to right
now." But, you put it off,
I guarantee you're probably not going to
want to do it. And the truth is, you'll
usually get back into momentum, and you
won't even want the distraction anymore.
You just got to create separation from
impulse to reaction. If that doesn't
work, let's add some friction. Let's
make it hard on yourself. It's kind of
like this fun game where I think about
it's easier to avoid the dragon than to
slay it. See, most people are like, "I'm
going to have food in my house." And I'm
like, "Well, then you're going to want
to eat that crap food." Versus if you
take the food and you put it out of the
house, then you got to get in your car
to go buy the food you shouldn't eat.
That made it hard. See how that creates
friction?
I like to make it easy for me to make
good decisions. So, I want to go to the
gym in the morning, so I prep all my
clothes so that when I wake up, it's
sitting there. My shoes, my clothes. I
pretty much told everybody, including my
wife, "I'm going to the gym in the
morning." So, there's no way I'm not
going to do it because everybody would
see it. Everybody would know. You have
to make it easy to make the right
choices. So, the cool part is is now
you've made it nearly impossible for you
to get distracted, or at least added
some friction. But, here's where most
people still get stuck. They sit down to
work and nothing happens because they're
waiting for a spark of inspiration,
something that might never come to them.
Which brings us to point number four,
building momentum. This is not what you
think it is. See, first gear is usually
easy to get into. Second gear is easier
because you're already in first gear and
then third gear is easier cuz now you're
in second gear and you have momentum.
The higher you go, the smoother the
shifts. Let me explain. When you're
driving a car and you got to put it into
gear, there's actually a lot of
mechanical friction to do that, right?
The first gear is always the hardest.
Then you get going, the engine revs up,
second gear, smoother, keep going, the
higher you go, the smoother the shifts.
By the time you're in third, fourth is
way easier. If you go from zero to
fourth, it doesn't work. And then once
you're going, fourth to fifth, you'll
barely notice because you're already in
momentum. And as a guy that literally
drives his cars every day doing donuts,
I know the power of mechanical momentum.
And most people will wait until they're
motivated, inspired, and feeling good
about their situation before they even
start and shift into first. You don't
need motivation. You don't need
inspiration. You don't need to feel it.
I say often times, just feel the
feeling, supply the plane.
What you need is to start. And if you
have the privilege of starting and being
in momentum, and you know when you're in
it, stay in it. Fight to be in it. I
think too many people give up their
power of momentum to anybody that's
willing to distract them. They sell
their dreams for cheap cheap prices
because they'd rather be distracted than
to be consistent. If you're staring at a
blank page, do anything.
If you're staring at yourself in the
mirror, you don't like what you see, go
for a walk. You can start a diet halfway
through a bag of chips and then you can
build momentum. You can decide to start
the business by calling anybody and ask
them to buy something. That first sale
means you're now in business. Momentum
is the key. The thing that stops people
from winning in general is they don't
have clarity around what they want to
do. So, step one, write down just the
steps of doing what you know you've been
avoiding, even if you don't make a
commitment to doing it. Try that. Then,
step two, pick anything that is a small
task that you could do that takes less
than 2 minutes. That's called the MINS,
most important next step. Then, if that
felt good, do another one. And then do
another one. And just start and build
momentum and go from first gear to
second gear to third gear. See, once you
have clarity and you know what you could
be doing and you take action and you get
some results, then you feel good and you
start to build and that is how we create
and stay momentum. So, often times, I
won't even make a commitment to doing
the project, I'll just be like, I'll
make a commitment to making a list of
things I know that I got to do if I
started the project. Then once I got the
list, I'm like, "Ooh, okay, maybe I can
do one of those." And then I do [music]
it. And then I say, "No, I'm like, I'll
do another one cuz that felt good." And
I do another one. And then I'm like,
"Ooh, I'm getting some feedback. It's
feeling good. I can see where the finish
line's going to come from." And then I'm
just like, "Oh my gosh, I can't believe
I thought I had to be motivated to even
start." So, now we got momentum, you're
in motion. But we got to make sure that
you're not just staying busy, we
actually have to be efficient in what
we're doing, which takes us to point
number five, doing the work efficiently.
That's where I use Parkinson's law,
which states the work expands to fill
the time you give it. I can't tell you
how often people say to me, "Hey man,
I'll get that to you by the end of the
week." And I go, "Why not Wednesday?"
"Well, I could do it Wednesday." "All
right, by when?" "End of the day." "Why
not noon?"
"Yeah, I could probably do it by noon."
"Cool. What changed from the first time
I asked for it to get done and me asking
if you can get it done sooner?" They're
like, "I don't know." It's like, "How
about we do that to ourselves?" So, I'm
a big fan of saying what is aggressive
but not impossible. Because if you
don't, you will just take up as much
time as you want to get the task done.
It's like when I go on vacation, the day
before I leave, I get everything that
are open loops done. Why? Because I know
the next day I'm gone for a while. So,
think about what's the mindset you had
before you went on vacation. How do you
live your day that way? See, if there's
no date, there's no priority, there's no
pressure, there's no execution. So, what
I've done is I've built a system on how
to do that, and it comes in three parts.
Here's how we go about it step by step.
One, we want to allocate specific
amounts of time to finish the task
[music]
and schedule in the calendar. I'm
talking a day of the week, a date in the
calendar, and a time of day. This is
called time blocking. And the reason I
do this is that the more you do it, the
more you'll learn to estimate properly.
Most people are always late because they
don't ever give themselves deadlines, so
they don't know if they overestimated or
underestimated. The second thing is at
the end of that time, schedule a meeting
with somebody else, or make a commitment
to show somebody the work that you did
during that time block. That'll create a
forcing function for you to get it done
because you know right after you're in
another meeting, or you promised to show
somebody the work you've done so far. It
basically creates a deadline you have to
stick to. And then the third step is
once I've committed to that time block,
I like to break it into 25 minute
chunks, which are called Pomodoros. And
then I have a timer that literally sits
on my computer, and it runs off every 25
minutes, and I got to focus on whatever
I wrote down I would get done in that 25
minutes, and I get it done. This system
creates a massive amounts of
productivity and accountability because
it gives you an efficient way to force
you to focus, to force you to stay in
momentum, to force you to get the thing
done. So, now that we've eliminated all
the distraction, we've built momentum,
and we've learned how to work
efficiently, here's the next thing. If
you stop here, you're going to have to
keep fighting yourself every single day,
forcing yourself to focus. It's going to
feel hard. It's going to feel
exhausting. So, the last step is to make
it easy and permanent.
Point number six, turning hacks into
identity. I remember one time I was
talking to Tony Robbins, and he said,
"The strongest force in human
personality is the need to stay
consistent with how we've defined
ourselves. The stories we tell ourselves
is our identity. It's our ego. And us
being consistent on how we see ourselves
is crazy powerful." So, the last step is
to turn those habits into identity so
you never have to think about them
again. So, for example, if I asked you
how many times did you have to stop
yourself from buying a vape when you're
driving home after work if you don't
vape? Probably never. Why? Cuz you don't
vape. You have an identity of that's not
who I am.
And eventually, a habit like going to
the gym becomes an identity, I'm an
athlete, and athletes go to the gym, and
athletes don't order pizza for lunch,
and athletes are very consistent in
their training, and athletes have
coaches. All of a sudden, that identity
drives your behaviors. And we want to do
that for your productivity. When it
becomes part of your identity, you don't
have to hack yourself anymore. I have an
identity that I'm the kind of person
that preps before meeting, that gets
done on time, that follows my calendar
100%, so I don't have to sit there and
stress myself out trying to do these
things because it's who I am. So, here's
what I want you to do. First off, we're
going to write one sentence, I always.
And I want you to finish this with
identity statements that essentially is
empowering. If you think about the
person who easily achieves the results
that you do in your life,
what do they always do? Do they always
work efficiently? They always put stuff
in their calendar? They always break
things down easier? They always meet
their deadlines? Write that down. And
the second sentence is I never. And
finish this with something that you no
longer want to do, or something you know
that's holding you back. Maybe it's a
vice.
I never eat after 6:00 p.m. I never play
video games. I never watch sports. I
don't know what it is for you. I know I
just said some crazy stuff, but ask
yourself, if I had to give up some
short-term distractions for long-term
dreams, what would those be? And write
down I never and insert that there. What
I always tell people is you have a 10.0
version of yourself that you could
become. And I think that person already
exists. You just got to start acting
like that person today. So, the key is
is to repeat those statements all the
time until your brain believes it, until
it becomes identity, until it becomes
just who you are.
So, now you've got everything that I
believe in avoiding the distractions to
staying focused and building momentum.
You just need to make a simple
commitment. Just start.
What work have you been avoiding? Where
is the potential for your next
breakthrough? Just write it below in the
comments. I'm going to read them all and
I want to know that you got what I was
sharing. And remember, if you haven't
already, find me on Instagram, Dan
Martell, two L's in Martell, and DM me
the word scale YouTube and I'll send you
over my full scale your business
workbook. And if you want to learn how
to make 2026 your best year ever, click
here and I'll see you on the other side.